If you have questions about moving to
Costa Rica, I don't have all the
answers, but I'll give you my real-life
experience. In this video, I'm going to
tell you about our property, how much it
cost, and when we bought it, and what
the process was like. Cuz buying land in
a foreign country is not exactly easy.
These are our goats. This is goat one,
goat two, and bee. In Spanish, bee, not
Billy. Bee. Coming to Costa Rica is very
easy. A US passport gets you 6 months in
this country. No visas required. Buying
property is a little different. You have
no rights as a US citizen in a foreign
country, so you have to form a
corporation. In order to form a
corporation, you're going to need a
lawyer. But, Costa Rica has more lawyers
per capita than any country on planet
Earth, and 95% of them are terrible.
There are no licenses required to sell
real estate in Costa Rica, so
everybody's a realtor. Everybody in
every little town is going to know
somebody with a farm for sale, and this
is what you have to be careful of
because Costa Rica has a maze of laws,
probably more than the US, and they
don't make any sense to me. And I'm a
professional real estate investor. I've
bought and sold 300 houses, but buying
one in Costa Rica was dicey even myself.
I think we looked at about 20 properties
before we settled on this finca, which
is 4 acres with six ponds containing
tilapia and lobsters. And then there's
about 120 fruit trees, including 30
mature cacao trees. Keep that in mind.
It's easy to build, but it's impossible
to grow something for 40 years in 1
year. There's also a sawmill, a big
workshop, group bathrooms, a main house,
a casita, an outdoor kitchen, and a
whole bunch of other Across the
street is a river with some
thousand-year-old trees that has a
Native American grinding stone covered
in moss sitting on the roots. This is a
pretty wild place. I looked at houses
that required you to cross a river in
your rental car. I looked at houses way
up at the top of the mountain with a
driveway you couldn't even walk up. I
looked at fancy houses by the beach.
Stay away from those. You need to be
very wary of anybody who speaks English
and is trying to sell you something.
Forming a corporation in Costa Rica is
pretty easy if you have a good attorney.
I would recommend you get one that
speaks English and Spanish because all
the documents are in Spanish, and if you
do not speak Spanish, you're going to
have a very hard time. If you have a
lawyer who speaks Spanish, he can
translate for you and also send you
documents in English.
formation process took about a month to
do and cost me about $1,200 USD. After
you form the corporation, you're going
to have to go find a property. Once you
find a property, it's a lot like the US
real estate transactions. You're going
to have to have a contract. There's a
due diligence. If you want an
inspection, you can have it, but then
you're going to hit the escrow part.
Escrow part is where they verify your
funds are not coming from narcoterrorism
of some kind. I don't know why it took
them a month to know that I wasn't a
narcoterrorist. I had to send no less
than 22 documents from my CPA in the US
to Costa Rica in order for them to
verify where my funds were coming from.
Once I was finally approved, I was able
to send the deposit and buy the
property. The easiest way to get
residency in Costa Rica is via
investment. The floor for residency via
investment is a $150,000 expenditure in
a property or a business here in Costa
Rica. Then you're going to have to
submit an FBI background check that's
apostilled and wait 6, 12, 18 months.
Everything moves a lot slower down here.
Hey.
That is a guinea fowl. That is one of
the most annoying birds you'll ever see.
It's kind of like a turkey, and
they lay hard eggs that are like their
hard heads.
It's like a broken donkey bird.
Donkey bird.
My bracelet came off and the chicken's
trying to eat it. I must point out that
I don't have residency yet, and I don't
really need it because I always leave
before 6 months is out. I'm a traveler
by nature, so you don't necessarily have
to have residency if you want to stay
here. You just have to leave every 6
months. We're about 2 hours from the
Nicaraguan border. We went with my buddy
Gary and spent the day retail shopping
up by Lake Nicaragua, and we came back.
They gave me a fresh 180 days on my
passport. Now back to the property
thing. There's a ton of things you have
to consider with Costa Rican property
that you don't with US property, and the
biggest one would be water rights. If
you do not have the proper water rights,
you are not going to get any water at
your property. You have to be very
careful because the real estate agents
and the lawyers are oftentimes complicit
with deals that don't have water rights.
They'll tell you, "Hey, you don't have
water, but you can just dig a well."
Well, that is true, but they're not
going to tell you that you'll get taxed
20% of the value of your property, and
there's like a 5- to 7-year waiting list
for wells. So you could buy the property
and then go to apply for a well, and
they say, "Yeah, that'll be like
$20,000, and we'll get to you in 5
years." You cannot live 5 years on your
property with no water, so beware. One
other thing are the surveys. About 10
years ago, Costa Rica changed to all
digital surveys with the national
registry, and but most of them still
have the old hand-drawn plats. If you
have a hand-drawn plat, it will not be
accepted. It will have to be converted
to digital. We looked at one property
that a hand-drawn plat that was 6 acres
different than the digital one, so you
have to be very careful. You could be
looking at this one plat, and it looks
like it's correct, but if it's
hand-drawn, it will not count. It will
have to be digitized. There's a maze of
laws that even I don't understand as a
professional real estate investor that
you're going to have to watch out for.
So the best thing is to get a good
lawyer that you can trust, and you
better know at least a little Spanish.
There's a ton of properties listed
online, but they're going to be inflated
like hell, guys. You have got to come
here to find what you're looking for.
Before I came here, I spent months
looking online at this property and that
property, but then when you go there,
it's not what it looks like online, and
the property doesn't matter. It's what's
around it. Costa Rica is full of
microclimates. You can be in one place
and then drive 20 minutes, and the
climate will be completely different. In
Costa Rica, there's a lot of cities I
term gringo cities. A gringo city is
basically Little America. There's a lot
of English signs, the prices are high,
and there's a lot of English-speaking
white people living there. I want to see
less of that here. I like traditional
Costa Rica out in the countryside with
ticos. Everything is pretty much for
sale in Costa Rica for the right price.
If you walk into any town as a white
man, there will be a number of people
who walk up to you trying to sell you a
property. Trust me, I know. I
experienced it. You can get hoes like
this. You need to have somebody that you
can trust, which is hard to find, and
you'll never find it unless you show
your ass up here. I was in this little
town called Bijagua in Costa Rica, and a
man walked up to me and said, "Are you
looking for property?" He saw I was a
gringo, and I said, "Uh yeah, why not?"
And he showed me this uh cacao
plantation he had, and I said, "Well,
how much is it? Cuánto vale?" And he
said, "1 billion dollars." I you
not. A billion for something that might
have been worth 250,000. So that's a
real-life example of how they will try
and sell you a dream, dude. There are no
appraisals here. It's a cash market.
Something is worth what somebody will
pay for it. fool and his money will soon
part ways. They do accept dollars most
places here, but the national currency
of Costa Rica is the colón. It
fluctuates up and down. Right now, it's
sitting about 475 colones to 1 USD. To
put that in perspective, you get a meal
for two for about 5 to 10,000 colones at
the local sodas. A soda is what they
call a little restaurant here, and
there's a ton of them. I love casados.
One of the biggest difficulties I had
was the speed of transactions here in
Costa Rica. Tico time is a real thing.
Everything moves slower here. In fact,
most expats leave because of the pace of
life. They can't handle how slow things
go. I would wait two or three days for a
response from the escrow people, and it
drove me crazy. They have something here
called tico time, hora de tico. If
somebody tells you they'll be there in a
tico hour, that means they'll be there
sometime today. I don't know what one
tico day means. That might be like an
entire month. So if you're trying to buy
something here, be prepared to go
despacio, amigo. It's going to move way
slower than you think. Do not try and
rush the process. If you rush, you are
going to make mistakes. They're looking
for people in a hurry who are not going
to read everything, going to miss the
details because Costa Rica is the land
of the spins. It's two faces. You can
get fleeced very easily. It's a very
safe country. They're not trying to rob
you, but they will fleece you if you
can, and if you're in a hurry, you stand
a good chance of being fleeced. If
you're looking to come to Costa Rica,
the first thing I tell you to do is
learn Spanish. You will automatically
have respect with the ticos for having
spent the time to learn their native
tongue. Do not sit at your computer in
the United States and look at houses to
buy in Costa Rica before you traveled
here. You have no idea what this
country's like. You don't know if you'll
like it here. You don't know if you'll
fit in. You don't know what the
climate's like. You don't know if you'll
assimilate. I cannot stress this enough.
If you have questions about Costa Rica,
just show up. You learn all this through
osmosis. If you bring your ass, your
brain will follow, and that's the only
way to learn and also the best way. They
do have a very good school system here.
Out here in the countryside, the kids go
to school for 5 hours a day. They only
get computers three times a week, and by
age 13, they're learning agriculture,
animal husbandry, how to cultivate
things. It's very realistic education.
When I volunteered to help the school
with the electrical work, they invited
me to eat lunch with the kids, and the
lunch was rice, a big bowl of garbanzo
bean soup with beef, and then a whole
box of fruit you could take as much as
you want, and a glass of fresh water.
The water here comes naturally as it
flows out of the top of the mountain,
runs through these blue tanks on the
side of the road. They don't even filter
it. They put a tiny amount of chlorine
way up at the top to kill anything that
might be in there, and that's it. It
comes out of the mountain to your house.
Last thing I'll tell you is the houses
are a little bit different here. The
houses invite you outside. There's not a
lot of air conditioning cuz you don't
need it. And I must point out that you
shouldn't be sitting around in your
house. If you come to this country, you
should be outside enjoying the wonderful
nature that they have. I don't want to
look at this dog, but there's a lot of
dogs in the street. These are not my
dogs, but they they come here all the
time. They belong to the neighbors. It's
a very happy little community here.
People are always out walking, and
they're very friendly. It's a very safe
community. There's never been a rape, a
kidnapping, or a murder of any kind
right here in this little city. Way
safer than any place I've ever been in
the US. Do not listen to those travel
advisories. And yes, you can trust me
far more than the United States
government. As far as the lifestyle
here, it's way better. I was a
competitive ultra runner for years
before I came to Costa Rica, and when I
got here, I lost 10 pounds. I went from
being a vegan ultra runner to working
out a lot less and eating whatever I
wanted here and lost weight. I look at
pictures of myself back in the States,
and you can see the difference when I'm
in Costa Rica. The stress just melts off
of you. There's not EMF from all these
towers. There's not radio waves going
through your body at all hours of the
day. There's zero chemtrails. I've not
seen a single chemtrail here in Costa
Rica. There's no heavy metals in the
water. There's no cameras in the street
corners. There are no addresses, no
mailboxes, and there are signs. If you
want to find out how to get somewhere,
you have to ask somebody. Welcome to the
1950s, baby. Buying stuff here has been
a process, but it's completely worth it,
and I tell you, if this is your dream,
just go chase it, man. That's what I
did. A trip to Costa Rica, I fell in
love with the place, and I determined I
wanted to come here, and I let nothing
dissuade me in the process. Chase your
dreams, man. I'd love to see all of you
sitting on your finca one day holding a
guinea feather in your hand from your
fowl. If you need some help along the
way, I might be able to help you. I'm a
busy guy. I run eight different
businesses in two different countries in
multiple languages with centimeters and
inches and dollars and colones, but I
will try and help you as much as I can.
But, remember, that's a job, not a
favor. I'm a busy guy, and I can't
answer all of your questions, but I try
and drop videos on here explaining what
it's actually like from a real
individual, not somebody trying to sell
you some My name is Joe Fells,
but you can call me Tico Joe, and I hope
to see you here one day. Pura vida, man.